<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soveraignes power, and the subiects duty: delivered in a sermon, at Christ-Church in Oxford, March 3. 1643. By J. Armagh.</title>
            <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E36_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E36[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soveraignes power, and the subiects duty: delivered in a sermon, at Christ-Church in Oxford, March 3. 1643. By J. Armagh.</title>
                  <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. Armagh = James Ussher, Archbishop of Armagh.</note>
                  <note>Actual place of publication conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The 4 in the imprint date is crossed out and altered to 1643.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155018:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Soveraignes Power, AND THE Subiects Duty: DELIVERED In a SERMON, at CHRIST-CHURCH in <hi>Oxford,</hi> March 3. 1643.</p>
            <p>By J. ARMAGH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 13.2.</hi>
               </bibl> Whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſisteth the Ordinance of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed for W.W. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:155018:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155018:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Roman. 13. verſ. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Let euery ſoule bee ſubiect to the higher powers: for there is no power but of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N vaine doe Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beare the Sword, if their ſubiects conſcience may queſtion their power. They which beginne it in the cauſe of Religion, may as well goe on, and doubt of all. And therefore as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are iuſtly zealous in reſtraining the outward man, the Prieſts ſhould bee as forward in informing the conſcience. You know the occaſion of ſuch a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and this hath put mee againe ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155018:3"/>ſoone vpon you and a new Text, ſtanding engaged for many, which I muſt deſire you to hearken to, as Gods meſſage, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the right of Kings by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom</hi> 13. <hi>v</hi> 1. <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe two parts: 1. a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition deliuered by way of command, expreſſing a duty enioyned, <hi>Let euery ſoule b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſubiect &amp;c.</hi> Wherein are three things,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Quis,</hi> Who it is that is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it <hi>Euery ſoule.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Quid,</hi> What it is, <hi>Be ſubiect.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Cui,</hi> To whom, <hi>The higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> 2. a Reaſon for confirmation of it, as if this cauſe were grounded, not onely on bare authority, but inforced by infallible reaſon, <hi>For there is no power but of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall begin with the perſons; and firſt with thoſe to whom this duty is due; <hi>the higher powers,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>We haue iuſt cauſe to examine this ſtile, and confine it ſtrictly to us ſubiect; leſt vſurpers taking aduantage of the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155018:3"/>ſecretly vndermine the bulwarke, which we hope for, and may heere build vp. For ſome are ready to thruſt in, and ſhrowd vnder this Title, Biſhops and all Spirituall Gouernours: others, who mainely oppoſe that, labour to make all temporall Gouernours equall ſharers; both which are repugnant to the Apoſtles meaning, and both equally dangerous. Let ſpirituall power be heere ſuppoſed, and (if they be not ſubiect) yet ſhall temporall Princes haue no command ouer the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. Let all temporall partake in it, and euery inferiour Magiſtrate ſhall conteſt with his King. For, for their ſafegard (according to them) as well as the Princes, is this precept of the Apoſtle. <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi> And heere is no ſubiection, but command al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted them. For <hi>powers,</hi> ſay they, extends its ſelfe to the ſpirituall power, and <hi>higher,</hi> in the others ſenſe, lookes onely on the people; and therefore agreeable to infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magiſtrates, who in reſpect of the people are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſuperexcellentes,</hi> exceeding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155018:4"/>all others in ciuill power. For that, which wee render <hi>Higher,</hi> they tranſlate, <hi>ſuperex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentes,</hi> hoping thereby to eſcape the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and danger of the vulgar tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which anſwers our Engliſh. That is <hi>Bezaes</hi> cenſure on the vulgar Latine, (which ſaith, <hi>Poteſtatibus ſublimioribus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita ſit</hi>) and redounds to our Engliſh; wherein he hath his followers. The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at firſt ſeemes onely verball, but when we heare them from hence ſuſpect a dangerous ſence; we are to ſtand vpon ourguard, and preſume of a reall diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Giue them leaue to change the word <hi>[ſublimioribus]</hi> into <hi>ſuperexcellentibus,</hi> and they thinke they haue ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in ſtead of abſolute Lords and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to put in Bailiffes and Conſtables. It muſt bee meant of all Magiſtrates, that haue power ouer other men, or elſe it is <hi>Periculoſa interpretatio.</hi> And wherin ſtands the danger? Becauſe they ſhall bee denied to deriue their power from God? That would not follow; becauſe others are hereſayd to bee of God, they being not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155018:4"/>named. Put the caſe they were denyed it, and had their power allotted them onely from Kings, and not immediatly from God, as Kings deriue theirs. Indeede this is that, which is much feared by them, who ſecretly labour to curbe Kings; as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare anon. But is this leſſe then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle giues them? <hi>S. Peter</hi> makes a different fountaine of power. <hi>Submit your ſelues to euery ordinance of man for the Lords ſake: whether it be to the king as Supreame; or vnto Gouernours, as vnto them, that are ſent by him:</hi> 1. Pet 2.13, 14. Gouernours, who haue a King, may not thinke they ſtand at the well-head with him; but haue their power deriued from him. By him are they ſent, and from him haue they their authoritie, and yet it is from God too, being a branch of the Kings power, which is immediatly from God. It is not then a dangerous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but the ſafeſt trueth which they would auoide.</p>
               <p>But we muſt not frame fancies, and then fit the Scripture to them by tranſlation. Indeed ſhould I lay this to their charge, I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155018:5"/>ſhould wrong them: for whileſt they were quarrelling with the word, that was the occaſion of daunger, rather then they would erre from the originall, they pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in another alike dangerous. For what aduantage haue they by <hi>Superexcellentibus?</hi> it is not in the comparatiue degree, as was the other. But hath it not a comparatiue ſenſe? Yes as great, or greater: Such as our Engliſh, <hi>more excellent, or more eminent</hi> doth not reach; which <hi>Pareus</hi> at length confeſſeth, ſaying, <hi>Praecipuètamen</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Apoſtle eſpecially aimes at the Supreame power; ſo the true meaning of the word importes: for it is that, which amongſt many is ſtill higher then them all, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Supreame,</hi> which our latter Engliſh Tranſlation obſerues in the place before cited out of Saint <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> Submit your ſelues to the King,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>as Supreame.</hi> They are then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Supreame</hi> powers only, to whom this obedience is due; and to all ſuch, whether in <hi>Monarchie, Ariſtocratie, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratie,</hi> or other forme of gouernement.</p>
               <p>This we haue further warrant for from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155018:5"/>our Apoſtles diſcourſe: for that wee may haue yet another Plea againſt <hi>inferiour Magistrates;</hi> and ſhew alſo at laſt againſt the Papiſts claime, that no <hi>Spirituall Power</hi> hath place here, theſe higher powers are ſuch,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> as to whom <hi>the ſword of iuſtice is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly committed,</hi> at the fourth verſe. He that is one of theſe powers, <hi>beareth not the ſword in vaine:</hi> for <hi>hee is the Minister of God, a reuenger to execute wrath vpon him that doth euill,</hi> and vnto whom Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute belongeth at the ſixth verſe: <hi>for this cauſe alſo you pay Tribute.</hi> Both which are the infallible markes of Supreame ciuill power, being parts of the Rights of Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. Yee haue then the perſons, to whom ſubiection is due. Let vs now ſee, <hi>Quis,</hi> who it is that is to performe it, whom wee find expreſſed by <hi>Omnis anima,</hi> Euery ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>PART. II. <hi>Quis? Euery ſoule.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat here the ſoule is vſed <hi>Synechdochicè,</hi> the part for the whole man (as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Scripture) I preſume needs no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155018:6"/>But yet there may be ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſe, why he nameth the ſoule, not the body: which <hi>Gorran</hi> will haue, <hi>Quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet eſſe voluntaria ſubiectio,</hi> as if he were not properly ſubiect, whoſe body was fitted to the Superiours command, and the will, which is from the ſoule, ioynes not with it. And <hi>Caietane, vt non ſolum corpus,</hi> to the end that Subiects ſhuld by the way vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that not only their bodie and goods, but <hi>ipſa anima,</hi> their very ſoule alſo ſhould be ſubiect to their Princes command; and as <hi>Omnis homo,</hi> euery man, ſo <hi>Totum bominis,</hi> or <hi>Totus homo,</hi> ſhould concurre to make a perfect obedience; for ſo our Apoſtle after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more plainely:
<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> Wherefore, <hi>ye muſt be ſubiect not onely for wrath, but alſo for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The maine thing wee are to enquire for here, is to know who theſe are, to whom this command extends it ſelfe, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as in the note, ſo in the Apoſtles mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there is an abſolute vniuerſalitie; ſo that no kinde of men, and no man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted; and it is worth our enquiry, ſince
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155018:6"/>there are not wanting who would wreſt themſelues out of this number.</p>
               <p>The Anabaptiſts at firſt would haue pleaded exemption from Princes, but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by their wofull experience, that they could neuer prooue it whileſt <hi>Powers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, haue changed their Propoſition, and in ſtead of putting themſelues out of <hi>Omnis anima,</hi> labour to ruine <hi>Poteſtates,</hi> not deeming them fit for Chriſtians. Theſe haue confeſſed their errour, and ſaue vs a labour.</p>
               <p>But the Clergie of <hi>Rome,</hi> aiming at the ſame priuiledge, &amp; managing their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more craftily; haue wreſted it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome Princes, which they haue now ſo ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully improued, that againſt Kings, by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent practiſe of it, and againſt all diſputers,
<note place="margin">Suarez def. Cath. fid. lib. 4. cap. 7.</note> by argument they challenge it as their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inheritance; &amp; maintain that the Pope cannot, if he would, ſubmit himſelfe to any ciuill <hi>Power:</hi> But were the ſword as able to pleade Kings cauſes in the field, as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines pens in the Schooles, their Crownes would not ſo often totter on their heads,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155018:7"/>nor their liues be expoſed to ſuch rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous out-lawes.</p>
               <p>That our Apoſtle intended this Precept to the Clergie as well as to the Laitie, if the words themſelues cannot perſwade, heare the Ancients expoſition of them. S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let euery ſoule bee ſubiect, yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> though he be an Apoſtle, yea, though hee be an Euangeliſt, or a Prophet, or whoſoeuer.</hi> Theodoret, <hi>Whether hee be Prieſt Biſhop, or Monke;</hi> So <hi>Theoph.</hi> So <hi>Oecumenius.</hi> And <hi>Bernard ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopum Senonenſem,</hi> vrging this verſe of S. <hi>Paul</hi> expounds it, <hi>Siomnis, &amp; veſtra,</hi> If euery ſoule be ſubiect,
<note place="margin">Bern. Epiſt. 42.</note> then yours. <hi>Quis vos excepit ab vniuerſitate?</hi> Who hath exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you from this vniuerſalitie? yea, and leaues a brande on all his ſucceſſours, that ſhall attempt to perſwade any Clerke to ſuch a freedome, <hi>Si quis tentat excipere, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur decipere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were theſe ſilent, the circumſtances at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this Epiſtle would diſcouer it. The occaſion, it ſeemes, of this ſtrict com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was the heathens iealouſie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155018:7"/>ſubiection, and the infection, which the Apoſtle feared, might haue ſeiſed on theſe new Chriſtians, from that common opinion of the Iewes, who were about this time altogether impatient of any gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but what they then expected from their Meſſias. For ſuppreſſing of the like conceit, and clearing of the Chriſtians, he addes this precept to the Epiſtle directed to all the Saints at <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore the Clergic; yea, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> too, (if hee were then in <hi>Rome,</hi>) elſe had he not ſatisfied, but encreaſed the Heathens ſupicion.</p>
               <p>Againe, this may be confirmed by the doctrine and practiſe of thoſe times. Our Sauiour takes order,
<note place="margin">Mat. 17.27</note> 
                  <hi>that Tribute be paid for himſelfe;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> giues direction to the Prieſts ſpies to giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that were <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 20.25</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> appeales to <hi>Caeſar</hi> for iudgement. And if wee looke backeward into the olde Teſtament, wee may finde the ſame ſubiection in Prieſts and Leuites, and the like power in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Superiours.
<note place="margin">1. Mac. 4.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas Maccabaeus</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Prieſt to <hi>Sanctifie the Temple,</hi> after
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155018:8"/>
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> his profaning of it. The like did <hi>Ioſiah.
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 34. Ib. Ca. 24.6. 1. King. 2.26. 1. Chro. 15 11.</note> Ioaſh</hi> reprehendeth <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the high Prieſt for neglecting it. <hi>Salomon</hi> depoſeth <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high Prieſt for offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. <hi>Dauid</hi> giues order to the Prieſts and Leuites for the ſeruice of God. <hi>Aaron</hi> is ſubiect to <hi>Moſes.</hi> But we may ſpare our labour for theſe arguments, ſince ſome of them are content to acknowledge the force of them, and graunt what wee haue prooued.
<note place="margin">Eſt. in rom. 1.1.</note> For ſo <hi>Eſtius</hi> to the practiſe of the Apoſtles, <hi>Non eſt conſequens,</hi> it followes not, if <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were then ſubiect to temporall powers, that therefore Biſhops and Prieſts ſhould be now. Why ſo? <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit Principibus Chriſtianis:</hi> Becauſe Exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath ſince beene graunted by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes. What? By the <hi>Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of euery dominion? If not, then are they not exempt from all. If ſo, it is but onely on fauour, and not of due; ſo that they are ſtill ſubiect, when any Prince ſhall claime it: Nay, they are neceſſarily ſubiect in the maine point of ſubiection, (if not in other circumſtances) becauſe an abſolute
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155018:8"/>freedome is a detraction from ſupremacy, which no perſon can diſpoſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we may conclude, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Prieſt, and euery perſon amongſt them is included <hi>in omnis anima,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt attend the charge that is giuen, <hi>Subdita ſit,</hi> Let it be ſubiect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>PART III. <hi>The Duty: Let it be Subiect.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>S. Chryſoſtome.</hi> He ſaith not ſimply, let it <hi>honour</hi> the <hi>powers,</hi> or be <hi>obedient,</hi> but let it bee <hi>ſubiect;</hi> which includes all parts of duty, which a ſubiect owes vnto his King; for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of which, no outward act of reuerence, or ſeruice muſt bee wanting: and though this may ſatisfie the Kings command; yet doeth not this diſcharge thee of thy duty, which can neuer bee true, till the heart anſwer the geſture of the body. Diuine precepts ſeaze not on the body onely, but the ſoule. If thou
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155018:9"/>wilt not then withdrawe thy ſelfe from this ſubiection, thou muſt adde theſe fowre conditions to thy externall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There muſt be in thee 1. <hi>Promptitudo voluntatis interior,</hi> a free, voluntary, and cheerefull aſſent of minde.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Sincerus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> perfect loue and affection towardes his perſon.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>Filialis timor,</hi> an awfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his power ouer thee, and a filiall feare of offending him.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. <hi>Fidelitas,</hi> a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart towards him, whereby thou art conſtant in all bonds of duty to him, and iealous of all iniuries by others intended againſt him. This is the qualification of the ſubiection heere mentioned, and when thus qualified, it is not arbitrary, left to thee, to performe when, and where thou pleaſeſt. For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> propoſeth it not by way of aduice, or direction; but <hi>imperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13</note> by way of command, hauing, beſides his apoſtolicall authority, the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, giuen by other his fellow-Apoſtles; by Chriſt himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Matt. 22.21</note> and the foundation of all commands, the <hi>Law,</hi> which was giuen by God himſelfe; firſt in generall termes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155018:9"/>
                  <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enlarged,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.12</note> 
                  <hi>That man that will doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, nor hearken vnto the Prieſt, or vnto the Iudge that man ſhall die.</hi> But doth this command vrge at all times, and on all occaſions? What if the Prince be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, idolatrous? The vices of the man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge not his power, and therefore not the Apoſtles command. If this might haue beene a ſufficient plea againſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>S. Paul</hi> might haue ſpared this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, ſince <hi>Nero</hi> was the <hi>power,</hi> to whom theſe Romans were ſubiect. Or (to omit all other caſes that may be made) what if his command be contrary to religion? yea an army bee rayſed for the extirpation of true religion? This is the true touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of ſubiection; and heere (if euer) may a ſubiect renounce all obedience to his King. For now is there <hi>power</hi> againſt <hi>power,</hi> man againſt God, and the ſubiect of both left to follow either man, or God. This is a wonderfull ſtrait, from which whileſt ſome labour to eſcape by the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of their faith, they turne traitors
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155018:10"/>to God: others by taking the ſword in hand, though but to defend, become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to their King: That is their ſtile.</p>
               <p>Whether God be to be obeied rather then man, ſhould need no proofe amongſt any that confeſſe a God: and therefore when a Chriſtian heares the commaund of a Prince preſſing him to what God hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden, Nature prompts him his anſwer, <hi>I muſt obey God;</hi> and this hath the Apoſtles practiſe ratified, who coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this their ſafe warrant for not yeelding to the High Prieſts iniunctions, <hi>Obedire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet Deo magis quam hominibus,</hi> we ought to obey God rather then man,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. de ve bis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, ſer. 6.</note> rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in reſpect of the danger that attends in the diſobeying of either; for, <hi>Hi carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>Ille gehennam minatur,</hi> theſe threaten impriſonment onely, God hell fire, I hey a temporall, He an eternall death. There is no ſhifting then of Gods command, without the penaltie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, and therefore he muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed euen againſt the King. That's my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the firſt caſe.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:155018:10"/>
               <p>But what if the King preſſe by violence to draw thee from that obedience, wilt thou maintaine it by violence?</p>
               <p>Wee haue indeed the Ieſuites inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for it, yea,
<note place="margin">Comoz let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> and the Popes encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to it: I ſpare the quotations becauſe there comes not a Booke of theirs, wherin (if occaſion be giuen) they forbeare to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſpin. Hiſt. Ieſuit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Anticotton.</hi>
                  </note> or compendiouſly to refer you to ſome: ſee <hi>Hospin.</hi> and <hi>Anticotton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A doctrine of which, when the Society is challenged for, they are aſhamed, and labour to cleere themſelues againſt their written teſtimonies, as appeares in <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet (I can not, but with griefe ſpeak it) we finde euen in ſome Reformed Bookes the Ieſuites penne. Their names deſerue to bee branded that broach ſuch poſitions: weigh thoſe of <hi>Pareus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Par. in Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>dub.</hi> 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhops and Paſtors may and ought to reſiſt their vniuſt Magiſtrates,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>1</label>
                  <note place="margin">Pareus <hi>his falſe doctrines and wicked po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Higher powers.</hi>
                  </note> not with the ſword but the word of God, reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their notorious impiety, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and reducing them to their office,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155018:11"/>according to the word of God, and the Law, and deliuering them, if ſtubborne, to Satan.</p>
               <p>That Prieſts ſhould tell Princes their faults,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Replic. </seg>
                  </label> we grant; but when they can vſe diſcretion, fitting ſo grand a buſineſſe; when they deſire to inſinuate into them by their owne teares, not enforce vpon them Gods command. Spirituall force is the mother of all other, but not farther to bee inſiſted vpon by mee at this time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our occaſion was from what follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Subditi non priuati,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label> ſed in Magistratu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriori constituti &amp;c.</hi> Subiects, ſuch as are inferiour Magiſtrates, may by armes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelues lawfully, the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, and true Religion againſt the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſuperior Magiſtrates are ſuch,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Replic. </seg>
                  </label> we may preſume, in whom the ſupreme po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer reſides; and then you may ſee how directly it thwarts the Apoſtles rule. For thoſe other Magiſtrate, are ſubiects.</p>
               <p>It is not lawfull for ſubiects,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> which are meerely priuate men, to take armes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155018:11"/>out a lawfull calling, neither to inuade a tyrant before danger, nor to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt them in danger, nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge themſelues after danger, if they may be defended by the ordinary power.</p>
               <p>If then they faile of this condition,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Replic. </seg>
                  </label> there is a time when they may right themſelues: we ſhall not need to collect it, he addes it in the following concluſion.</p>
               <p>If a tyrant preſſe on his ſubiects,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>4</label> as if he were <hi>latro</hi> and <hi>stuprator,</hi> and they can not eſcape by flight, or any other ordinary meanes, it is lawfull for to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and theirs, as againſt a priuate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner.</p>
               <p>How far ſhort theſe concluſions come of the Ieſuites poſitions, I referre to your trial by comparing them. And yet is not he the only man that maintaineth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi> and the fayned <hi>Iunius Brutus</hi> are infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for this doctrin. I could name others But this may ſuffice that there is ſcarce any of them, who are eager for the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and are fit inſtructours in this point for ſubiects of a free Monarch; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155018:12"/>no maruell if our eares bee tainted with ſuch doctrine.</p>
               <p>That which I conceiue in this caſe for truth is, that no ſubiects may vpon any occaſion take armes or vſe any violence againſt the ſupreame power, no not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.2</note> ſayth S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 2. verſe. Which place may well ſerue to confirme Princes <hi>power</hi> ouer their ſubiects in this caſe; for this rule was giuen to them, who ſuffered vnder a Tyrant, and that for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. It is a vaine and idle exception, which <hi>Pareus</hi> takes at this. Some argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from the power of Maieſty, ſaying, ſuch places are bent againſt <hi>priuate</hi> men, who vſurpe ſuch power ouer ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; for euery Common-wealth conſiſts but of two ſorts in the generall, Prince and People, ſuperiours and ſubiects: thoſe who partake not of the Supremacy (as in an Oligarchie) are priuate men: if (where the power is deuided) one take the ſword againſt the other, this is as hee is a part of the ſupreame power.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:155018:12"/>
               <p>Other arguments that may bee drawne <hi>à parte potestatum,</hi> I forbeare, becauſe they haue all their ſtrength from the Apoſtles reaſon, and till that be weighed, we cannot auoide their ſhifts.</p>
               <p>If we reflect vpon ſubiects, we ſhall find that their hands are tied by precepts, which lay hold on them, as they take on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be zealous Chriſtians. Chriſts,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44. Rom. 12.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Pray for them that perſecute you:</hi> and the Apoſtles, <hi>Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to no man euill for euill;</hi> are not ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vertues, but that they pertaine to euery man; yea, it is the onley badge of their true ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Chriſt, if for his Names ſake they practiſe them. And therfore <hi>Tertullian</hi> inſtead of abetting ſuch zealous reuenge, fights with a prohibition,
<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. c. 37. Ad Scap.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſit vt igne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano vindicetur ſecta diuina; at doleat pati, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo probatur:</hi> and in the combate gaines the victory, by the perſecutors cruelty, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth it, <hi>Crudelitas vestra, eſt gloria nostra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince precepts are made ſo liable to diſtinctions; and, when capable of ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall expoſitions, each may be maintained; let vs read the expoſition of them in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155018:13"/>practiſe of them, that gaue and receiued them. Did our Sauiour or his Apoſtles euer withſtand the rage of the perſecuting Iewes? Doe wee reade of any one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roare, or reſiſtance made by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Chriſtians in thoſe barbarous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, practiſed on them by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Idolatrous Tyrants? No, but in ſtead of alarums for defence, they reioyced, when apprehended, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd in their torments; hauing yet their hearts alwayes as ready to wiſh and pray for the happie ſtate of their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, as their bodies readie to ſuffer their violence. I might prooue it from age to age, for many hundreds of yeeres after Chriſt: but that I can but touch, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe this queſtion, and leaue it to your owne reading, and further ſcanning. The force of this argument is confeſſed by our oppoſites, who thinke to relieue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by imputing their not reſiſting to their weakenes, not vnwillingnes to reſiſt. Raſh vncharitable Iudges of ſuch holy Saints. Did they proclaime one thing to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155018:13"/>the world, and belie the thoughts of their hearts? Heare their vnanimous conſent in <hi>Tertullian; Apud nostram diſciplinam occidi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis licet, quam occidere;</hi> It is our profeſſion, rather to die then kill. Such precepts, and the rules of obedience kept out al thoughts of rebellion againſt their Prince; and hence in their name <hi>Tertullian</hi> contends with his heathen Perſecutors for a greater ſhare in <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in whoſe name they were execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>Noſter eſt magis</hi> Caeſar;
<note place="margin">Apol. c. 33.</note> He is rather ours, then your Emperour, being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our God. And where as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend want of force in Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">Soc. hiſt. lib. 3.9.</note> they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not, that at <hi>Iulians</hi> death, his whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie cryed out to <hi>Iouianus,</hi> We are all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. In <hi>Diocleſians</hi> time, <hi>Omnes ferè mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales,</hi> The whole world almoſt, leauing their Idolatrous Sacrifices, ioyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the Chriſtian Congregations. <hi>Tertullian</hi> pleads againſt the ſame obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; would wee deale with you as enemies,
<note place="margin">Apol. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Deeſſet nobis vis numerorum, &amp; copiarum?</hi> could we want forces? We Chriſtians haue filled all places of your Empire, your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155018:14"/>Ilands, Caſtles, all but your Temples. Yea goe higher yet, and behold the Church in her cradle, arm'd with force able to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the world, the Apoſtles power of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Chriſts legions of Angels, ready to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e employed at his command. Or had they failed of theſe meanes, they thought of as eaſie a tricke as the Ieſuites, to puniſh their enemies, when <hi>Tertullian</hi> profeſſeth, that one night, by the helpe of a few tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, might haue afforded them a large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge. Behold now the power of theſe Primitiue Chriſtians, and yet weltring in their own blood for their Chriſtianitie: With them, to right themſelues vpon their perſecutors, or to oppoſe them, is rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and malice. Then was it the ſtrongeſt parts Plea; <hi>Laeſos vltio diuina defendit</hi> (as Cyprian) Diuine refuge protects vs.
<note place="margin">Tract. con. Demet. pa. 224.</note> But now, Our owne arme ſhall ſtrengthen vs. It is a glorious plea with fleſh and blood, to fight the Lords battell, and to prouide that the true Religion be not rooted out: and (for ought I find) their beſt argument, for all the reſt hang on the diſpoſing of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155018:14"/>Power,</hi> (which by the Apoſtles reaſon are all vndermined) or on the example of ſome, whoſe commiſſion is confeſſed to be extraordinary, and from God. But let them heare whether we may not take vp Saint <hi>Hilaries</hi> complaint;
<note place="margin">Hil. con. Auxent.</note> 
                  <hi>Miſereri licet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae aetatis laborem, &amp; praeſentium temporum ſtultas opiniones, quibus patrocinari Deo huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na creduntur, &amp; ad tuendam Chriſti Eccleſiam ambitione ſaeculari laboratur;</hi> Wee may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pitie the vaine labour and fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of theſe times, wherein mans endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours are accounted Gods aid, and Chriſts Church thought to be maintained by the worlds policie, ambition or greatneſſe.</p>
               <p>For the Apoſtles receiue a ſharpe checke that would haue fire come downe from heauen, to conſume the rude Samaritans;
<note place="margin">Luke 9.54.55.</note> and the ſword that was drawne in Chriſts defence is commanded to bee put vp into his place, not without the heauie ſentence: <hi>All that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.52.</note> Whence <hi>Tertullian,
<note place="margin">Tertul. de Cor. Mil.</note> Gladium nec Dominicae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſioni neceſſarium reddidit.</hi> The ſword was not lawfull in a priuate mans hands; no,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155018:15"/>not for Chriſts ſake. The weapons which the true Church vſeth in her battels,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4</note> are ſpirituall: and the walles of Iericho are not to be battered, but with the Prieſts trumpets.</p>
               <p>Proteſtants ſhould remember how they withſtand the Papiſts notes of the Church when they require it to be viſible, of large extent, and glorious in the eie of the world. And Papiſts ſhould acknowledge what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> profeſſeth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm. de Ecc. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Durauit hucuſque &amp;c.</hi> The Church hath laſted to this day in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of her enemies, Iewes, Pagans, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes; and not ſo onely but ſtill hath gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by perſecution. That is the greateſt aduantage, that true Chriſtianity hath when it is perſecuted; and then doth ſhee conquere, when her ſouldiers are ſlaine. Was the Proteſtants cauſe weakened, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in France, by their many outragious maſſacres; or in England, by their frequent fiers; or in the Low Countries, by their great afflictions? If euer they prooue loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, it is when they vniuſtly fight for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing it. Should the Papiſt Princes all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155018:15"/>muſter their forces,
<note place="margin">Scioppins claſſ. ſacr.</note> and wage the holy warre, whoſe Trumpet hath already ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the alarum, they might perchance for a time eclipſe the light of trueth, put it out they neuer can. They may abate the viſible number, but will make more true Profeſſours. <hi>Tertullians, Sanguis Martyrum est ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> is a maxime, The bloud of true Martyrs is the Churches ſeeds-plot, if it be caſt into the fire, or ſpilt by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſted ſword.</p>
               <p>I could dwell in the contemplation of this ſtrange husbandry; but that I may be ſuſpected for digreſſing, and am yet to ſhew the <hi>medium</hi> betweene <hi>diſobeying</hi> God, and <hi>reſisting</hi> the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is confeſſed there muſt bee no diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying of God: That wee may not reſiſt the King is prooued (as the occaſion giues leaue) what then remaines? <hi>Preces &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae,</hi> ſollicite, beſeech, earneſtly pray for the reuerſing of the Decree, <hi>Haec ſunt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimenta ſpiritualia, &amp; tela diuina, quae prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt,</hi> This is the only ſhelter and fortreſſe, whither a Chriſtian may betake himſelfe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155018:16"/>in this tempeſt.
<note place="margin">Heſter 3.16</note> Heere was <hi>Heſters</hi> and the Iewes refuge, when the Decree was gone out from <hi>Ahaſueroſh</hi> for the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Iewes.
<note place="margin">Act. 4.2.</note> Hither fled the Apoſtles, when they were prohibited to preach Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 28</note> 
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> of Conſtantinople, when command was giuen for the reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Arius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruſſin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 36.</note> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> when hee was eagerly proſecuted by <hi>Iuſtina</hi> in the cauſe of Arianiſme. And theſe are <hi>tela</hi> too, and <hi>diuina,</hi> weapons that fight from aboue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fury of perſecutours; not, as if by thee directed to reuenge (that is not warrantable) but approoued with God by the teſtimonies of his vengeance. By theſe was <hi>Hamans</hi> gallowes (appointed for <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi>) fitted for himſelfe; by theſe on the day, when <hi>Arius</hi> ſhould haue beene reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, did he ſodainely periſh by theſe was <hi>Iuſtina</hi> put to flight and executed. If theſe preuaile not, know that now is the time wherein God will make triall of thy faith to him, and loyalty to thy king. Both which muſt appeare in thy readineſſe to vndergoe the intended affliction.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:155018:16"/>
               <p>There is no <hi>defenſiue reſiſtance</hi> allowed, vnleſſe thy defence be ſuch,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3.</note> (as <hi>Liuie</hi> only allots to ſubiects) <hi>Scutum, non gladius,</hi> the buckler of patience, not the ſword, which is as ready to giue, as ward the blow. Hee that in this defence wounds his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, is a rebellious <hi>murtherer,</hi> not a lawfull <hi>executioner.</hi> Remember that he is ſtill thy Prince, and ſince thy conſcience may not yeeld to his command, ſhew thy ſelfe his ſubiect in yeelding to his puniſhment. For now thou maye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t either die by liuing, or liue by dying: Thou haſt Chriſts war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it; <hi>Hee that</hi> (in ſuch a caſe) <hi>findeth his life ſhall looſe it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.39</note> and hee that looſeth his life ſhall finde it;</hi> looſe a temporall, finde an eternall, where he ſhall for euer raigne in the glory of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Martyrs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
